Whyte, William Foote Additional Papers /4087
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
William Foote Whyte Additional Papers
1928-1990
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Whyte, William Foote
/4087
8 cubic feet
8 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
3086193
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
C. Tan, June 27, 2011
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, September 30, 2016
Biographical / Historical
William Foote Whyte (June 27, 1914-July 16, 2000) was a sociologist chiefly known for his ethnographic study in urban sociology, Street Corner Society. Whyte, from an upper middle class background, showed an early interest in writing, economics and social reform. After graduating from Swarthmore College, he was selected for the Junior Fellows program, where his landmark research was done. After his research in Boston, he entered the sociology doctoral program at the University of Chicago. Street Corner Society was published by the University of Chicago Press in 1943. He spent a year teaching at the University of Oklahoma, but developed polio in 1943 and spent two years in physical therapy at the Warm Springs Foundation. Rehabilitation was only partially successful; Whyte walked with a cane for the rest of his life, and used two arm crutches in his later years. He briefly returned to the University of Chicago in 1944, then joined the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University in 1948, remaining at Cornell for the remainder of his career. He worked for social reform and social change, directing his efforts toward "empowering the disenfranchized and narrowing the gap between rich and poor." He studied industrial and agricultural workers and workers' cooperatives in Venezuela, Peru, Guatemala and in the Basque region of Spain, as well as in the United States. He authored hundreds of articles and 20 books including an autobiography. He is considered a pioneer in industrial sociology.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /4149 AV: "ASA Award Presentation to William Foote Whyte by Jacqueline Scheier" Audio-Visual Materials /4058: William Foote Whyte Office Records /4094: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4102: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4149: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4151: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4163: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4168: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers /4173: William Foote Whyte Additional Papers
Whyte, William Foote,1914-2000.; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations --Faculty.
3086193
- Langone Politics, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Nortons, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Notes and Papers Street Corner Society Structure + Informal Groups, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Racketeers Lives and Businesses, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Nortons and Leadership I; List of Nicknames, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- The Nortons- Leadership II, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Nortons Following I VU, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Langone Politics II (Fitzgerald), 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- "Chichi", 1937 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Leo's Coffee House, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- North End Clippings, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Race Relations: The Irish vs. the Italians, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Misc. Beginnings - Housing Survey, etc., 1937 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Religion and The Feasts, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Miscellaneous, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- The Mass March, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Slum Sex Code, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Richmond and North Streets Jannes Club, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Original 13, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Settlement House, Recreational Centers, 1937-1939 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- J. Howard's Material, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- John F. Fitzgerald Clippings, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Social Anthropological Study of a North End Family- Jimmy Spatz, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- DiCarlis, Christine Serra, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- The Racketeer in the Cornerville S. and A. Club, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- SCS Orientation Literature- Nature of City Life, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Political Meetings, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Police and Politics, 1937-1942 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- North North End, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Politics and the Local Structure, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Book II, Part I. The Social Structure of Racketeering, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- The Nortons and their Leader, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- The Rise and Fall of the Community Club, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Two Worlds [folder 1 of 2] (Box 4, Folder 34)
  Scope and Contents
  pp.1-271. Handwritten. Photocopy.
- Two Worlds [folder 2 of 2] (Box 5, Folder 1)
  pp.272-559. Handwritten. Photocopy.
- Articles by Whyte, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Misc. Notes Part I, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Misc. Notes Part II, 1939-1941 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Misc. Notes Part III, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Hanover Associates, 1939-1941 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Italian Fellowship League, 1937-1940 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Phillips Petrol Part I, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Phillips Petrol. Part II, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- People in Petroleum, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Report on the Radisson- Manuscript, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Chandler's Restaurant Part I, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Chandler's Restaurant Part II, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Phillip's Correspondence, 1943-1944 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Phillips Part I, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Phillips Part II, 1942-1943 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Plans for Organizing Studies, 1936-1937 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Letters on Writings, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Notes on North End, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Phillips Co. Letters, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- North End Letters, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Misc. Letters, 1937-1939 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Plans, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Letters on St. Corner Society, 1941-1944 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Personal Letters, 1939-1941 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- North End Letters, 1937-1942 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- College Writings, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Various Letters, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1935 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Grade Reports, 1928-1934 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Buchsbaum I, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Buchsbaum II, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Stouffer's Notes I, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Stouffer's Notes II, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Stouffer's Notes III, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Marshall Field Restaurant Interviews, 1944-1945 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Correspondence and Clippings, 1953-1968 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Union-Management Cooperation, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Sidney Garfield, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Phillips, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Inland Steel Container, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Inland Steel Container Documents I, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- Inland Steel Container Documents II, 1948-1950 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Inland Steel, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Restaurant Association/ Restaurant Book, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Unwritten Book (Loomis-CMA) Research Group, 1942-1943 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Research Group, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Oklahoma Teaching Notes, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Bundy, continued, 1945-1947 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Bundy Paper, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Age Grading, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Chicago Teaching, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- Rocco #1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Rocco #2 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Swarthmore Writing (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Novel "Campaign" (Box 7, Folder 4)
- North End Fiction (Box 7, Folder 5)
- North End Fiction - cont. (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Municipal Finance (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Govt. + Business Paper, 1934 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Bill Whyte Writings (Box 7, Folder 9)
- TVA Project (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Text digitized from the collection. (Box 8)